A Register of the Vladislav Al'bionovich (Vl.)Maevskii Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Subject file, 1869-1978 and undated. (Box 29)
  - Kartashev, Anton V., 1913-1966 and undated. (Folder 30: 6)
    Clippings, notes, biography compiled by Bishop Kassian
  - Khorvat, Dmitrii L., 1933-1937 and undated. (Folder 30: 7)
    Clippings, biographical sketch
  - Kolesnikov, S. F., 1957-1962 and undated. (Folder 30: 8)
    Clipping, correspondence relating to Kolesnikov, notes
  - Krasnov, N. N., 1955-1956. (Folder 30: 9)
    Typescript, incomplete, of "Nezabyvaemoe"
  - Lermontov, Mikhail Iu., undated (Folder 30: 10)
    clippings
  - Masonry, undated (Folder 30: 11)
    clipping and notes
  - Nikolaev, K. N., 1927-1964 and undated. (Folder 30: 12)
    Clippings and notes. Includes Prorocheskii smysl russkoi literatury deviatnadtsatago vieka, signed by author
  - Orthodox Eastern Church (Box 31)
    - Bell ringing, 1892- and undated (Folder 31: 1)
    - Conciliarity, 1962-1967 and undated. (Folder 31: 2)
    - Doctrines. Life after death, 1935-1946 and undated. (Folder 31: 3)
      Includes materials on burial practices, and liturgical commemoration. Articles, clippings
    - Eastern patriarchs, 1954-1966 and undated (Folder 31: 4)
    - Liturgical music, 1946-1966 and undated. (Folder 31: 5)
    - Liturgics, 1903-1960 and undated. (Folder 31: 6)
      Clippings, notes, pamphlet by A. A. Dmitrievskii
    - Moral theology, 1946-1969 and undated. (Folder 31: 7)
    - Pascha, 1913-1970 and undated. (Folder 31: 8)
      Article drafts, clippings, notes
    - Poland--History--20th Century.
      - General, 1924-1945 and undated (Folder 31: 9)
      - Grodno diocese, 1926-1964 and undated. (Folder 31: 10)
        Clippings, correspondence
    - Sunday of Orthodoxy, undated. (Folder 31: 11)
  - Pushkin, Aleksandr S., undated (Folder 31: 12)
  - Rasputin, Grigorii, 1963 and undated. (Folder 31: 13)
    Clippings, correspondence, drafts, notes
  - Romanov, House of, 1955-1962. (Folder 31: 14)
  - Rossiiskoe edinstvo, 1962 and undated. (Folder 31: 15)
    Includes open letter to Metropolitan Anastasii (Gribanovskii)
  - Russia--History
    - General, pre-1917.
      - 1917-1959 and undated (Folder 31: 16)
      - 1960-1973 (Box-folder 32: 1)
    - Monarchy, 1956-1964 and undated. (Folder 32: 2)
      Clippings and notes
    - Peter I, 1972. (Folder 32: 3)
  - Russia--Relations--France, undated. (Folder 32: 4)
  - Russia--Relations--Middle East, 1909-1914. (Folder 32: 5)
  - Russian composers, 1951-1965 and undated. (Folder 32: 6)
  - Russian literature, 1869-1953 and undated. (Folder 32: 7)
  - Russian Orthodox Greek Catholic Church of America
    - General, 1926-1972 and undated. (Folder 32: 8)
      Includes bulletin, and clippings
    - Adam (Filipovskii), Bishop, 1933-1937. (Folder 32: 9)
      Includes materials relating to the consecration of Bishop Adam
    - Autocephaly, 1964-1970. (Folder 32: 10)
      Includes articles and clippings
    - Collected correspondence
      - Afanasii (Shelepov), Abbott, 1954 and undated (Folder 32: 11)
      - Amfilokhii (Vakul'skii), Bishop, 1924-1929 (Folder 32: 12)
      - Arsenii (Chakhovtsev), Bishop, 1924-1937 and undated. (Folder 32: 13)
        Includes letters to various hierarchs including Metropolitan Feofil, lists of clergy, minutes, reports, resolutions, and other documents pertaining to Russian Orthodox jurisdictional conflicts in the United States
      - Borichevskii, S. D., Reverend, 1943 (Box-folder 33: 1)
      - Feofil (Pashkovskii), Metropolitan (before 1934 – Archbishop), 1925-1946 and undated. (Folder 33: 2)
        Includes letters from Metropolitan Platon (Rozhdestvenskii), Bishop Leontii (Turkevich), Bishop Antonin, Bishop Arsenii (Chakhovtsev), Bisop Pavel (Gavrilov), Archbishop Sergii (Tikhomirov), and attorney Stephen S. Parfenoff
      - Gerasim (Shmal'ts), Archimandrite, undated (Folder 33: 3)
      - Nikon (Greve), Archbishop, undated (Folder 33: 4)
      - Platon (Rozhdestvenskii), Metropolitan, 1924-1929. (Folder 33: 5)
        Includes letters from Archbishop Feofil
      - Tkachuk, Igor, Reverend, 1967 (Folder 33: 6)
      - Turkevich, Leonid (later – Metropolitan Leontii), 1926-1957 and undated. (Folder 33: 7)
        Letters addressed to Archbishop Feofil (Pashkovskii). Includes clippings of poems
      - Yonov, Alexis, Reverend, 1970 (Folder 33: 8)
    - Councils
      - General, 1935-1970 and undated. (Folder 33: 9)
        Includes agendas, correspondence, minutes, notes, reports
      - Council of Bishops, 1933-1936. (Folder 33: 10)
        Includes acts, circular, epistles, minutes, related correspondence
      - 8th All-American council, 1950. (Box-folder 34: 1)
        Acts, printed matter
      - 9th All-American council, undated (Folder 34: 2)
        typescript of informational mailing
      - 10th All-American council, 1959-1960 and undated. (Folder 34: 3)
        Clippings, notes, reports, speeches
    - Hierarchs, 1927-1957 and undated. (Folder 34: 4)
      Includes Blagoviestnicheskie trudy v Amerikie mitropolita Platona
    - History, undated. (Folder 34: 5)
      Untitled typescript dealing with jurisdictional conflicts in the United States within Russian Orthodoxy
    - Ioann (Shakhovskoi), Archbishop, 1952-1971 and undated (Folder 34: 6)
    - Schmemann, Alexander, Reverend, 1962-1970 and undated. (Folder 34: 7)
      Includes clippings and notes
    - St. Tikhon's monastery, 1938-1950. (Folder 34: 8)
      Clippings, commemorative brochure
    - St. Tikhon's Orthodox Theological Seminary
      - General, 1955-1958 and undated (Folder 34: 9)
      - Clippings, 1949-1953 and undated (Folder 34: 10)
      - Course materials, 1951-1954 (Folder 34: 11)
      - Course schedules, 1958-1959 (Folder 34: 12)
      - History, 1950-1958 and undated. (Folder 34: 13)
        Includes materials relating to council meetings
      - Minutes, 1949-1958 (Folder 34: 14)
      - Reports, 1950, 1960 (Folder 34: 15)
      - Rules, 1949 (Folder 34: 16)
    - St. Vladimir's Orthodox Theological Seminary, 1960-1968 and undated (Folder 34: 17)
  - Russian Orthodox Theological Fund, Inc., 1959 (Folder 34: 18)
  - Russians--Foreign countries
    - General, 1946-1967 and undated (Folder 34: 19)
    - China, 1955 and undated (Folder 34: 20)
    - United States, 1942-1978 and undated (Box-folder 35: 1)
    - Yugoslavia, 1928-1965 and undated (Folder 35: 2)
  - Russkaia osvoboditel'naia armiia, 1961-1973 and undated. (Folder 35: 3)
  - Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov'
    - Appeals, 1912-1916 and undated. (Folder 35: 4)
      Printed copies, includes appeals for the construction of churches, schools, and for orphans
    - Correspondence. Aleksandr (Nemelovskii), Archbishop, 1927-1929 (Folder 35: 5)
    - Exarchate of Ukraine, 1928. (Folder 35: 6)
      Copy of minutes of council held in Kiev on January 25, 1928
    - Grushko, Stefan, Reverend, 1931. (Folder 35: 7)
    - History, 1939-1966 and undated. (Folder 35: 8)
    - Medvedev, Matvei, Reverend, 1954-1968 and undated. (Folder 35: 9)
    - Parish life, undated (Folder 35: 10)
      clipping and article draft
    - Platon (Rozhdestvenskii), Archbishop of Katalinsk and Kakhetinsk, undated. (Folder 35: 11)
      Calling card
    - Russian ecclesiastical mission, 1917-1967 and undated. (Folder 35: 12)
    - Teodorovich, Terentii, Reverend, 1930-1938 and undated. (Folder 35: 13)
      Includes handwritten articles, clippings and correspondence
    - Tikhon (Belavin), Patriarch, 1968. (Folder 35: 14)
    - Valaamskii monastyr', 1966. (Folder 35: 15)
  - Russkaia pravoslavnaia tserkov' zagranitsei
    - General, 1926-1969 and undated. (Folder 35: 16)
    - Anastasii (Gribanovskii), Metropolitan, 1953. (Folder 35: 17)
    - Antonii (Khrapovitskii), Metropolitan, 1903-1962 and undated. (Folder 35: 18)
      Includes article draft, clippings, notes
    - Ariadna (Michurina), Abbess, undated (Box-folder 36: 1)
      typescript
    - Bogoroditse-Skorbiashchinskii sobor, San Francisco, 1948-1963. (Folder 36: 2)
      Clippings, includes materials relating to the court proceedings
    - Correspondence
      - Apollinarii (Koshevoi), Archbishop, 1924-1926. (Folder 36: 3)
        Letters addressed to Archbishop Feofil (Pashkovskii)
      - Filaret (Voznesenskii), Metropolitan, 1965 (Folder 36: 4)
    - Councils, discussion of, 1925-1965 and undated. (Folder 36: 5)
      Clippings, notes, includes copy of letter from Archbishop Serafim (Ivanov) to Metropolitan Anastasii (Gribanovskii) pertaining to Archbishop Ioann (Maksimovich)
    - Epistles, 1926-1966 and undated (Folder 36: 6)
    - Filaret (Voznesenskii), Metropolitan, 1957. (Folder 36: 7)
    - Nafanail (L'vov), Bishop, undated. (Folder 36: 8)
      Includes clipping and biographical materials
    - Nikon (Rklitskii), Bishop, 1953 and undated. (Folder 36: 9)
      Clippings, notes. Includes materials on Tsarskii viestnik
    - Our Lady of Kazan Russian Orthodox Church, Sea Cliff, N.Y., 1959-1971 and undated. (Folder 36: 10)
      Clippings, correspondence and related materials
    - Polemics, 1927-1965 and undated. (Folder 36: 11)
      Clippings, brochures dealing with jurisdictional matters
    - Vremennoe polozhenie, 1935 and undated. (Folder 36: 12)
      Includes related epistle and minutes of council meetings
  - Russkii okhrannyi korpus, 1956-1961 and undated. (Folder 36: 13)
  - Russko-amerikanskii institut, 1963 and undated. (Folder 36: 14)
  - Russkoe studencheskoe khristianskoe dvizhenie, 1953-1964. (Folder 36: 15)
  - Seniavin, D. N., Admiral, 1949-1953 and undated. (Folder 36: 16)
    Article drafts, related correspondence, notes
  - Serbia--History, 1916-1972 and undated (Folder 36: 17)
  - Serbian Orthodox Church, 1882-1967 and undated (Box 37)
    - General, 1931-1969 and undated. (Folder 37: 1)
      Includes article drafts, clippings, and notes
    - Correspondence, 1882, 1957 and undated. (Folder 37: 2)
      Letters from various Serbian Orthodox clergy
    - Gavrilo (Dozhich), Patriarch, 1935, 1953. (Folder 37: 3)
    - Nikolaj (Velimirovic), Bishop
      - General, 1951-1967 and undated. (Folder 37: 4)
      - Biographical materials, 1957 and undated (Folder 37: 5)
      - Clippings, 1946, 1955 and undated (Folder 37: 6)
      - Correspondence, 1954-1955 (Folder 37: 7)
      - Personal notes, 1952-1955 and undated (Folder 37: 8)
    - Schism, materials relating to, 1956-1964 and undated (Folder 37: 9)
    - Varnava (Rusich), Patriarch
      - General, 1935 and undated. (Folder 37: 10)
      - Correspondence, 1922 and undated. (Folder 37: 11)
        Letters and petitions. Correspondents include Metropolitan Antonii (Khrapovitskii), Reverend Grigorii Lomako, Bishop Mitrofan (Abramov), Archimandrite Vitalii (Maksimenko)
      - Obituaries, 1937 (Folder 37: 12)
      - Personal notes, 1911-1918 (Folder 37: 13)
    - Printed matter, 1963-1964. (Folder 37: 14)
      Brochures
  - Serebriakova, Galina, undated. (Folder 37: 15)
    Clippings from Novoe russkoe slovo of Serebriakova's memoirs
  - Shmelev, Ivan S., 1947-1960 and undated. (Box-folder 38: 1)
  - Solzhenitsyn, Alexander I., 1972 and undated (Folder 38: 2)
  - Soviet Union
    - Church history, 1947-1956 and undated. (Folder 38: 3)
    - Description and travel, 1965-1972. (Folder 38: 4)
    - History, 1925-1939, 1955-1967 and undated. (Folder 38: 5)
    - History--Revolution, 1917-1921, 1938-1972 and undated. (Folder 38: 6)
  - Sukachev, L. P., 1972. (Folder 38: 7)
  - Timashev, N. S., 1963-1967 and undated. (Folder 38: 8)
  - Tolstoy, Leo (Folder 38: 9)
    - Clippings, related notes, 1908-1971 and undated
    - Research notes, undated (Box-folder 39: 1)
  - Ukraine--History. General, 1964-1969 and undated. (Folder 39: 2)
  - World War (1914-1918), undated. (Folder 39: 3)
  - World War, 1939-1945--Concentration camps, 1961-1967 and undated. (Folder 39: 4)
  - World War, 1939-1945--Soviet Union, 1949-1954. (Folder 39: 5)
  - Young Men's Christian associations, 1930-1967 and undated. (Folder 39: 6)
    Clippings relating to the YMCA's activities in relation to the Russian church and Russian émigrés
  - Yugoslavia--History, 1964-1969 and undated. (Folder 39: 7)
- Photographs, 1900-1970 and undated.
  One hundred and ten prints, and four negatives
  - Unidentified landscape, undated. (Folder 39: 8)
    One print
  - Unidentified library and illuminated manuscripts, undated. (Folder 39: 9)
    Eighteen prints
  - Evangelie kneza Miroslava, undated. (Folder 39: 10)
    Four negatives, eight prints
  - German (Doric), Patriarch, 1970. (Folder 39: 11)
    One print, signed
  - Hierarchs, 1962 and undated. (Folder 39: 12)
    Three prints – Bishop Nikolai (Velimirovich), signed print of Archbishop Nikon (Rklitskii), and one print of Archbishop Vitalii (Maksimenko)
  - Leontii (Turkevich), Metropolitan, 1951. (Folder 39: 13)
  - Nikolaev, K. N., 1959. (Folder 39: 14)
  - Russian convent of Our Lady of Vladimir, 1958. (Folder 39: 15)
    Twenty four prints, includes related letter
  - Russian émigrés, 1936-1964 and undated. (Folder 39: 16)
    Four prints
  - Shmelev, I. S., 1926-1946. (Folder 39: 17)
    Three prints
  - Teploukov (?), P., 1906-1913 and undated. (Folder 39: 18)
    Three prints by M. Tagrin of Kremenchuk, two prints are signed
  - Varnava (Rusich), Patriarch, 1900-1935 and undated. (Folder 39: 19)
    Thirty four prints
- Oversize file, undated.
  Boxes 40-41 contain a collection of one thousand and thirty one prints relating to Athos. Not filmed. Boxes 42-43 contain scrapbooks with articles pasted by the author
  - Athos, 245 and 786 prints of churches, monasteries, monks, landscapes. Not filmed (Box 40-41)
  - Scrapbooks, articles pasted by the author (Box 42-43)
- Printed matter, undated. (Box 44-54)
  Brochures, clippings, postcards. Clippings from various Russia émigré newspapers and other sources. Includes brochures, postcards. Not filmed